<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.1/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <title>Patient Safety Overview</title>
    <para>Integrated Knowledge Exchange (IKE) is a set of principles, tools and methods that are
        designed to make doing the right thing easier. One of those “right things” is patient
        safety. First and foremost, our health information must do no harm to the patient. IKE
        enables more accurate, complete, precise, and higher-quality health data that is safer to
        use for clinical decision-making. Low quality health data management practices can lead to
        under treatment, over treatment, or delayed treatment resulting in preventable patient harm.
        [16]</para>
    <section>
        <title>Patient Safety – Then and Now</title>
        <para>Patient safety has been defined as the “prevention of harm to patients.” [17] To
            achieve patient safety, the whole system of healthcare must prevent errors, learn from
            the errors that occur, and develop a culture of safety similar to other high-risk
            industries such as aviation.</para>
        <para>Patient safety efforts have mostly focused on investigation of adverse events after
            they have occurred. This is <emphasis role="bold">reactive safety</emphasis> and while
            important for learning from errors, it is insufficient in reducing common adverse events
            such as medication errors, surgical complications, or diagnostic errors. [18]</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Proactive safety</emphasis> attempts to design or redesign
            systems, processes, and methods based on leading indicators of increased risk, poor
            quality, or identified flaws <emphasis role="italic">before</emphasis> an adverse event
            occurs. Examples of proactive safety practices include hazard analysis, safety
            reporting, audits, tracers, training, testing, and surveys to measure the culture of
            safety.</para>
        <para>Developing a <emphasis role="bold">culture of safety</emphasis> includes establishing
            a non-punitive response to error which is also known as a just culture. Just culture is
            a balance between learning from error and accountability. [19] Absent a just culture, it
            is unlikely practitioners will self-report errors due to fear of retribution, loss of
            employment, or legal action. Blaming an individual or team for system errors prevents
            learning from errors, impedes continuous improvement, and reinforces silence when system
            vulnerabilities are discovered.</para>
        <para>Since the 1999 report, <emphasis role="italic">To Err is Human</emphasis>, was
            published by the Institute of Medicine, patient safety has received more attention
            across the healthcare ecosystem due to the prevalence of preventable patient harm. A
            short review of these important patient safety publications documents key milestones for
            system improvement opportunities and required changes to reduce preventable patient
            harm.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">To Err is Human (1999)</emphasis></emphasis> –
                    described the breadth and depth of preventable harm and the challenge of
                    improving patient safety. It was estimated that nearly 100,000 Americans died as
                    a result of preventable patient harm. [20] In 2016, a study from Johns Hopkins
                    researchers estimated annual patient deaths at more than 250,000 Americans
                    making preventable patient harm the 3 <superscript>rd</superscript> leading
                    cause of death in the USA behind cardiac disease and cancer. [21]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Crossing the Quality Chasm
                            (2001)</emphasis></emphasis> – described the quality gaps in healthcare,
                    how current practices degrade quality, and how to take systems approaches to
                    improve quality. Aims for quality improvement included safety as system
                    property, effectiveness, patient-centeredness, timeliness, efficiency, and
                    equity regardless of gender, ethnicity, geographic location, or socio-economic
                    status. The report furthered the need for digitized health information systems.
                    [22]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Health IT and Patient Safety
                            (2012)</emphasis></emphasis> – described both the promise of health IT
                    and the potential patient safety risks of poorly designed, improperly
                    configured, and mismanaged electronic patient data and health IT systems. The
                    report further highlighted the importance of the human-machine (including
                    software) interface to prevent diagnostic errors and improve clinical decision
                    making. Health IT vendors, regulators, and health systems were encouraged to
                    find ways to mitigate identified health IT risks and the unintended consequences
                    of the <emphasis role="italic">Meaningful Use</emphasis> criteria as part of the
                    Health Information Technology for Economic and Clinical Health (HITECH) Act of
                    2009. [23]</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Improving Diagnosis in Health
                            Care (2015)</emphasis></emphasis> – described the importance of reducing
                    the prevalence of diagnostic errors across the healthcare system including
                    missed diagnosis, delayed diagnosis, and incorrect diagnosis resulting in
                    undertreatment, overtreatment, suboptimal standard of care, and preventable
                    patient harm. It is estimated that every American will experience at least one
                    diagnostic error during the lifetime. High quality health information is
                    critical for improving diagnostic decision making. Clinicians and patients must
                    be able to trust the underlying health data and health IT systems being used for
                    diagnostic decision making. [24] </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">High reliability organization</emphasis> (HRO) principles from
            other safety critical industries such as commercial aviation and nuclear power began to
            be adopted as a patient safety framework in some healthcare settings (See Table 1). [25]
            The principles originated from social science as behaviors present in organizations
            which operated in extremely complex, high-risk environments with high levels of system
            reliability believed to produce safer outcomes. Reliability is the probability that a
            component or system will perform as designed under certain conditions over time (e.g.,
            checklists). Leaders and managers can foster a culture supported by HRO principles that
            focuses on reducing errors at a single component level, also known as component failures
            (human or machine). [26] Limitations of this approach can seduce leaders into believing
            that worse case scenarios (losses, adverse events, accidents) have linear causality with
            the human as a possible weak link in the system. HRO methods rely on decomposition
            (breaking complex systems down into single components to analyze) rather than using
            systems theory to address highly complex, highly coupled systems such as healthcare data
            information systems. [27]</para>
        <table>
            <title>HRO Principles for Health Information</title>
            <tgroup cols="3">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
                <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">HRO Principle</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">HRO Response</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">IKE Application</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Preoccupation with Failure</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Develop leading safety indicators</entry>
                        <entry>Measure &amp; monitor data quality</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Reluctance to Simplify</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Awareness of active &amp; latent failures</entry>
                        <entry>Identify known &amp; unknown defects</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Sensitivity to Operations</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Promote reporting of defects</entry>
                        <entry>Speak up &amp; report errors/defects</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Commitment to Resilience</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Manage errors before losses occur</entry>
                        <entry>Perform rigorous testing/monitoring </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis role="bold">Deference to Expertise</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Engage experts in decision making</entry>
                        <entry>Use informatics experts in health IT</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>Traditional safety approaches have become inadequate to address the increasing
            complexity of healthcare due to rapidly emerging technology, big data, and the advent of
            artificial intelligence (AI) across a dynamic health information ecosystem. To address
            the increasing complexity, healthcare institutions are beginning to leverage systems
            theory, systems thinking, and a systems approach to safety. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">System Safety </emphasis>is rooted in systems theory where the
            whole, the designed system, is more than the sum of the parts. System Safety addresses
            the whole using a combination of systems and safety engineering approaches. Traditional
            safety methodologies such as root cause analysis (RCA) and Failure Modes and Effects
            Analysis (FMEA) focus on failures at a component level or as over-simplified human
            error. RCA and FMEA were developed before work systems incorporated software, computers,
            and other sophisticated technology such as AI. System Safety views patient safety as a
            control problem. </para>
        <para>Engineering models can be developed and analyzed for safety and quality purposes
            throughout the system’s lifecycle from design through adoption. These system models are
                <emphasis role="italic">not</emphasis> schematics or flow charts; instead, they
            serve as abstract representations of highly complex sociotechnical relationships between
            a controller and the process being controlled. These relationships are known as control
            loops (Figure 1). [28]</para>
        <figure xml:id="Provider-PatientControlLoop">
            <title>Provider-Patient Control Loop</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../images/Provider-Patient%20Control%20Loop.svg" scale="35"
                        align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Control loops are hierarchical with the <emphasis role="italic">Provider</emphasis> as
            a controller above the <emphasis role="italic">Patient</emphasis>, the controlled
            process in this example. The downward arrows represent the control actions that the
            controller uses to control the patient care process including assessments, exams, tests,
            imaging, treatments, and therapies. The upward arrows are feedback mechanisms the
            provider receives from the patient such as their medical history, symptoms, and health
            trends. </para>
        <para>Without adequate feedback, the provider would not be able to make safe, high quality
            clinical decisions that meet the standard of care. The <emphasis role="italic"
                >Provider</emphasis> controller develops a process model or belief system about each
            individual patient before making treatment decisions. Other information may be
            accessible through the patient’s EHR, a family member, or another patient advocate.
            Modelling the patient care system of interest builds on this control loop to include
            other essential control loops forming what’s known as a control structure. [29]</para>
        <para>Once the control structure is fully modelled, either in the design or redesign phases
            of the system lifecycle, teams can conduct proactive and retrospective safety analyses
            to identify new requirements, system hazards, unsafe control actions, and missing
            feedback loops. The System Theoretic Process Analysis (STPA) method is most effective
            when used early in the design or redesign phase as a prospective safety analysis while
            the Causal Analysis based on Systems Theory (CAST) is used retrospectively to determine
            causal factors of adverse events such as preventable patient harm. [30] </para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Safety Management Systems (SMS) </emphasis>are used by high-risk
            industries such as aviation, military commands, health care, and nuclear power to reduce
            or eliminate hazards for safer outcomes. SMS is a formalized approach to safety
            decision-making, proactive safety management, safety culture promotion, and quality
            assurance. An effective SMS relies on a comprehensive safety information system that has
            leading indicators of safe performance, feedback from voluntary reporting, and passive
            data collection using software applications that monitor system control actions. </para>
        <para>Safety data trends are reported to responsible parties including operators,
            supervisors, management, regulators, and other industry stakeholders. An SMS is an
            enabler for learning including knowledge sharing, policy effectiveness, and innovation.
            Key processes of an SMS include safety risk management and safety assurance. [31] SMS
            design is enhanced when system control structures are modelled, monitored, and audited
            using system safety engineering principles such as STPA. </para>
        <para>Safety in a health data context includes clinical decision support, safe data
            exchange, and safe use of health data for regulatory oversight, research, and population
            health decision-making. Furthermore, poor data quality degrades patient safety
            especially among disparate health populations when using low quality data to train AI
            models for patient care. [32]</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Spotlight Case Study #1: STPA of the U.S. Diagnostic Laboratory
                Data Ecosystem</emphasis></para>
        <para>The STPA of the U.S. Diagnostic Laboratory Data Ecosystem, was a proactive analysis
            that sought to detail the operations of the complex, interdependent system both as a
            whole and of its respective components within and identify where – or where not –
            diagnostic laboratory data was fulfilling its goals of higher quality care. </para>
        <para>Using STPA with interviews from 50 stakeholders, the research team developed a model
            of the ecosystem (control structure) and analyzed it to identify the causal factors in
            common types of adverse events related to diagnostic laboratory data and provided
            recommendations for improvement and system redesign. This analysis identified over
                <emphasis role="bold">200</emphasis> unsafe control actions (UCAs) and six main
            causal factors that contribute to two main recurring hazards: (1) patients receiving
            less than adequate care and (2) diminishing trust and/or reputation within the
            laboratory data ecosystem. </para>
        <para>These six causal factors with their associated recommendation were:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Decentralized and missing oversight</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 1: Assign responsibility for addressing gaps in the
                            regulatory oversight of laboratory data exchanges between system
                            components that are regulated by different agencies.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 2: Identify the data and standards needs of regulatory
                            agencies and ensure they have the ability to use them
                            appropriately.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 3: Encourage the identification of regulatory gaps in
                            other areas of the laboratory ecosystem through additional
                            systems-theory-based analyses.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Inadequacies and gaps in laboratory data standards, including standards that
                    are loosely constrained, ambiguous, and outdated</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 4: Reference libraries must develop a knowledge base
                            that establishes a ground truth for naming, coding, and mapping of
                            reference terminologies to particular laboratory tests, and stakeholders
                            must be incentivized to use it.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 5: Appropriate groups must be assigned responsibility
                            for identifying gaps and weaknesses in laboratory data standards and for
                            establishing a reporting channel for problems related to them.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 6: Standards Development Organizations (LOINC®, SNOMED
                            CT®, RxNorm, etc.) must continuously support users by identifying and
                            eliminating ambiguities in implementation guides for HIT
                            standards.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Inaccurate perceptions of risks with respect to both laboratory data and the
                    use of  HIT</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 7: Proactively and retroactively investigate systemic
                            sources of diagnostic error.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 8: Create a consolidated national database for HIT
                            safety reporting that can be used to identify trends and opportunities
                            for improving patient safety outcomes. It should include information
                            about HIT not behaving as users intended and allow understanding how
                            features of HIT design may have contributed to “user errors.”</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Lack of a systems view by participants in the system</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 9: Educate the healthcare community on systems
                            engineering and systemic approaches for solving problems, including
                            tools to accomplish this goal.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 10: Establish appropriate control loops for updates to
                            standards and HIT.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Inadequate regulatory emphasis on the safety involved in health system
                    information technology</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 11: Assign regulatory oversight of HIT safety to ONC or
                            another appropriate group. Include the explicit directive to develop and
                            include safety-related certification criteria for HIT and the ability to
                            limit the inclusion of “hold harmless” clauses in HIT contracts.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 12: Establish incentives for using certified HIT
                            throughout the entire healthcare ecosystem.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Flawed communication and coordination</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Recommendation 13: Develop formal processes for inclusion of
                            laboratorians in the multidisciplinary teams responsible for decisions
                            about laboratory data needs, representations, and interfaces at care
                            facilities.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">UCA Scenario – Defining the Need for IKE</emphasis></para>
        <para>This following UCA identified during the STPA in Spotlight Case Study #1 where IKE
            solutioning would strengthen knowledge representation, improve data quality, and reduce
            patient risk.</para>
        <para>UCA scenario: A medical practitioner may provide treatment that does not match the
            patient’s condition. One contributing factor may be that the practitioner does not have
            the diagnostic information to inform their mental model of the patient’s condition. The
            diagnostic information may not be observed by the medical practitioner because they may
            be accustomed to using their routine process to access results in the EHR, which only
            displays laboratory data that has been previously mapped to the care facility’s EHR
            system (e.g., mapped to a LOINC® code or local code representation). In some cases,
            additional unmapped test results are shared by the laboratory as a PDF and the physician
            may not notice due to its lack of salience in the EHR process flow. Physicians who are
            not expecting or looking for the test results may not be prompted to look for
            additional, unmapped information in a patient profile, particularly if the unmapped
            results were ordered by another physician or a long time ago. The results may have been
            shared as a PDF because they pertained to a new or uncommon test whose format could not
            be represented in the messaging standard available to that laboratory-care facility
            pair. Standards for new and complex tests (e.g., genomics) are not yet tightly
            constrained and can be shared as PDFs because Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments
            (CLIA) only requires that the data sent gets received and does not specify the method of
            transmission nor impose any requirement or confirmation that the information is observed
            by the medical practitioner. CLIA was drafted and approved in 1988, before EHRs were
            widely adopted and modifications to CLIA require Congressional approval. The following
            is a visualization of this scenario using system safety principles (Figure 2). </para>
        <figure xml:id="VisualizationofUnsafeControlActionUCALaboratoryDataScenario">
            <title>Visualization of UCA Laboratory Data Scenario</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata
                        fileref="../images/Visualization%20of%20Unsafe%20Control%20Action%20(UCA)%20Laboratory%20Data%20Scenario.svg"
                        scale="35" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>For the full report, click <link
                xlink:href="https://synensysglobal.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/12/System-Safety-within-Laboratory-Data-Exchanges-Report.pdf"
                >here</link>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The Promise of Digital Health Information and Patient Safety</title>
        <para>In the U.S., moving from paper charts to EHR systems is mostly complete (96%) with
            only 22% of office-based physician practices remaining paper-based. [33] Incentive
            programs such as <emphasis role="italic">Meaningful Use </emphasis>(MU) provided
            government funding through CMS for health systems and provider organizations to digitize
            their health information systems. From 2010-2020, MU program goals included digital data
            collection, data sharing, advanced clinical processes, and improved outcomes. Studies
            have shown that HIT has improved patient safety by reducing medication errors, avoiding
            adverse drug reactions, and increasing adherence to evidence-based medicine protocols.
            [34] While HIT has improved some clinical outcomes, the adoption, configuration,
            implementation, and maintenance of HIT has increased patient risk in other parts of the
            health delivery system due to unintended consequences of poorly managed HIT. [35]</para>
        <para>First-generation HIT configurations have mostly been managed by HIT vendors who mainly
            focused on billing data and other administrative and operational data management
            functions (e.g., reimbursement, mandatory reporting, etc.). HIT adoption radically
            changed historic clinical workflows in an effort to standardize data inputs and system
            outputs. This “one size fits all” approach was resisted by clinicians creating
            configuration trade-offs, workarounds, and increased system complexity. </para>
        <para>Local configurations and local coding created unique HIT features and functionality
            which may have been needed based on a hospital location or patient population while also
            creating variability from hospital to hospital possibly within the same health network.
            For the most part, these local variations had few initial negative consequences for
            patients and health practitioners. Unfortunately, most HIT configurations did not
            optimize for patient mobility – patients who received care in non-affiliated systems or
            for the need to share precision data with other agencies such as health registries and
            public health agencies.</para>
        <para>Without new incentives, many organizations are unable to fully maintain aging HIT as
            vendor maintenance contract costs continue to increase. Also, experienced HIT personnel
            are more expensive as other technology companies search for qualified staff in a
            decreasing talent pool. Health systems have become more dependent on vendors to fill the
            talent gap. Some under-resourced hospitals may be forced to delay system upgrades and
            updates – even important changes in terminology, clinical workflows, naming and coding,
            or other critical data quality enhancements due to concerns over system failures,
            outages, or unexpected consequences from system updates. These are real concerns and may
            lead to patient safety implications. The recent CrowdStrike cybersecurity update failure
            in 2024 caused many health systems to cancel surgeries and other non-critical services
            leading to over $2 billion in losses to healthcare organizations. [36]</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Addressing patient safety gaps in the current health data
                ecosystem</emphasis></para>
        <para>Today, health data is critical to health care decisions. Mostly, we focus on data used
            to make clinical decisions because those decisions directly impact the treatment that
            patients receive, and the quality of care delivered. Clinical decision support systems
            (CDSS) depend on data accuracy and precision to ensure decision “triggers” fire when
            appropriate to prevent delays in treatment or diagnostic errors. If important clinical
            information is missing sufficient context, decision-making can be incorrect,
            insufficient, or incomplete. A laboratory test result that is missing units of measure,
            reference range, or unique device identification may not be used for decision-making
            prompting further testing, additional costs, and unnecessary patient suffering for
            intrusive tests. Patient history may not always be accurate or complete – especially
            when migrating data from one EHR to another especially when data migration is limited to
            recent history.</para>
        <para>Many of the types of errors related to encoding, sharing, and exchanging health data
            remain difficult to manage safely since institutions are mostly interested in the
            quality of the data received rather than the data sent. The Assistant Secretary of
            Technology/Office of the National Coordinator for Health IT (ASTP) has developed the
            Trusted Exchange Framework and Common Agreement (TEFCA) to enhance data sharing and data
            exchange. The framework establishes policies, governance practices, and standards aimed
            at making health data more accessible for payers, public health agencies, provider
            organizations, and patients. TEFCA will likely enhance the data sharing infrastructure,
            it does not currently address the quality of data being shared. [37]</para>
        <para>Data intended to be used for research needs to possess the attributes summarized in
            the Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability, and Reusability (FAIR) Guiding
            Principles, which provide guidelines to make data findable (F), accessible (A),
            interoperable (I) and reusable (R) to the research community and machines.
            Unfortunately, a large portion of health data does not meet the FAIR Guiding Principles
            as it is often hidden in isolated data silos and incompatible systems and difficult to
            exchange, process, and interpret. [38-39] During the COVID-19 pandemic, leaders were
            unable to make informed decisions related to public health because of incomplete data,
            unstructured data, and missing data leading to preventable patient deaths, pandemic
            response delays, and unnecessary lockdowns. [40]</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Interoperability and patient safety</emphasis></para>
        <para>More to add</para>
        <para>Use Long Dozen Interoperability content</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Data standards and standardization</emphasis></para>
        <para>More to add</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Data quality – what are the patient safety
                implications?</emphasis></para>
        <para>More to add</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Spotlight Case Study #2: Analysis of laboratory data
                transmission between two healthcare institutions using a widely used point-to-point
                health information exchange platform: a case report</emphasis></para>
        <para>The objective of this analysis was to identify information loss that could affect
            clinical care in laboratory data transmission between two health care institutions via a
            Health Information Exchange (HIE) platform. To accomplish this, data transmission
            results of 9 laboratory tests of a simulated patient, including LOINC® codes, were
            compared in the following: between sending and receiving EHR systems, the individual HL7
            Version 2 messages across the instrument, laboratory information system, and the sending
            EHR. The analysis found that the loss of information for this and similar tests
            indicated the following potential patient safety issues: </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Consistently missing specimen source</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Lack of reporting of analytical technique or instrument platform</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Inconsistent units of measure and reference ranges</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Discordant LOINC® code use</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Increased data messaging complexity with multiple HL7 versions</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para> </para>
        <para>This analysis showcased the challenges surrounding the completeness and accuracy of
            laboratory data exchanges in terms of the data elements required by law and the needed
            details to correctly interpret the results of the test. Additionally, this analysis
            highlighted the differences of manufacturers’ equipment (specifically in vitro devices)
            performing the same test on the same sample and the production of differing results.
            Furthermore, despite being key to correct interpretation, information on the equipment
            manufacturer that produced the result, and the type of sample tested was never included
            in the exchange results. The study concluded that while the SHIELD collaborative
            community recommendations can be helpful − such as consistently including encodement
            information (SNOMED CT® and LOINC®), Unified Codes for Units of Measure (UCUM), and
            Unique Device Identifier (UDI) – these are partial steps to improving laboratory data
            interoperability. In tandem, EHR and LIS functionality must be standardized to allow for
            the consistent capture and transmission of relevant data elements. Usage of a HIE with
            standard messaging, SHIELD recommendations, and enhanced EHR data encoding functionality
            can yield consistent test identification and result value transmission. </para>
        <para>For the full study, click <link
                xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/jamiaopen/article/7/2/ooae032/7657767"
                >here</link>.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Spotlight Case Study #3: Establishing Trust in Pharmaceutical
                Data with an Independent Verification and Validation (IV&amp;V)
                Methodology</emphasis></para>
        <para>In this study, researchers demonstrated a general-purpose IV&amp;V approach for
            information models, instance data, and knowledge that will enable reproducible metrics
            for data quality and patient safety. This IV&amp;V approach uses established statistical
            process control methods for inter-rater and intra-rater reliability and agreement
            metrics with Cohen’s Kappa to evaluate pharmacy prescription data being migrated between
            a legacy EHR and commercial-off-the-shelf (COTS) EHR. These methods are widely accepted
            in other industries where quality and safety are closely monitored, but the methods are
            under-utilized within the HIT industry. The research team demonstrated that these
            methods can be applied to electronic health data and knowledge management tasks.
            Researchers recommended that HIT practitioners routinely use bivariate comparison of
            reviewer agreement over an appropriately sized statistical sample to develop standard
            benchmarks for health data and knowledge quality and safety. A detailed description of
            the method is provided in this study along with summarized analysis findings from the
            application of IV&amp;V methods to pharmacy prescription data being migrated between
            EHRs.</para>
        <para>For the full study, click <link
                xlink:href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10148340/">here</link>.</para>
    </section>
    
</section>
